Hi and welcome back to Rock the JVM's Scala at Lightspeed. I'm Daniel and in this video we will
はい、Rock the JVMの「Scala at Lightspeed」にお帰りなさい。Danielだよ。この動画では
discuss one of Scala's most powerful features which is pattern matching. Now I'm going to go
Scalaの最も強力な機能のひとつ、パターンマッチングについて話していくよ。じゃあ
back to the project that we created at the beginning of this mini course and if you are
このミニコースの最初に作ったプロジェクトに戻るね。もし
new to this video series go back to the beginning of the course where we set up this initial project
この動画シリーズを初めて見る人は、最初の動画に戻ってプロジェクトのセットアップと
and we discuss the infrastructure that we are going to use throughout this series. Now under
このシリーズで使うインフラの説明を確認してね。じゃあ
the package com.rock.jvm that I created at the very beginning I'm going to create a dedicated
最初に作ったcom.rock.jvmパッケージの下に、この動画用の
application for this video so I'm going to right click new Scala class I'm going to name this
専用アプリケーションを作るよ。右クリックしてNew → Scala classで、名前を
pattern matching I'm going to make it an object as we did with the previous applications and I'm going
PatternMatchingにして、前の動画と同じようにobjectにするよ。そして
to have it extend app so that we can actually run this so you can run this on your own computer
Appをextendsして実行できるようにするね。自分のパソコンで
if you want to test some code. All right now the first thing that I'm going to talk about pattern
コードを試したい人はこれで実行できるよ。さて、まずパターンマッチングについて
matching and let me collapse my menu so that you can see my code is what you may have seen in other
話していこう。メニューを閉じてコードを見やすくするね。他の
programming languages like Java or C or C++ which is the switch statement.
プログラミング言語、JavaやCやC++で見たことがあるかもしれないswitch文の話から始めるよ。
So I'm going to use pattern matching as some kind of a switch expression.
パターンマッチングをswitch式のように使うところから見ていこう。
What do I mean by that? Let me create a value of a type int let's call this an integer as having the
どういうことかというと、Int型のvalを作って、anIntegerという名前で
value 55. Now you can match this integer against a number of cases instead of using if else chains
値を55にしよう。このanIntegerをif-elseチェーンの代わりにいくつかのケースに対してマッチングできるんだ。
so let me give you an example let me define a value called all ordering or order as and watch what I'm
例を見せるね。orderというvalを定義するよ。よく見ててね。
writing an integer space match which is a keyword in Scala and then I'm going to open and close some curly
anInteger スペース matchって書く。matchはScalaのキーワードだよ。そして波括弧を
braces and inside I'm going to add cases so in case I get one I will return the string first in case I get
開いて閉じて、中にcaseを追加していく。case 1なら文字列"first"を返す、case 2なら
I will return the string third and in case I get everything else which is denoted by this underscore
"second"を返す、case 3なら"third"を返す。そしてそれ以外の場合、このアンダースコアで表される
the equivalent of the default case in the other languages I will return an integer plus the suffix
他の言語でいうdefaultケースに相当するものだけど、整数値に"th"というサフィックスを付けて返すよ。
th so if I want to print line this order value so print line order I will return 55th which is the
このorderの値をprintlnすると、println(order)で、55thが返ってくる。
description of the number 55 it takes a bit of time to compile so 55 th now notice this this pattern
55の序数表現だね。コンパイルにちょっと時間かかるけど、55thだ。ここで注目してほしいのは、
match structure is actually an expression so pattern match is an expression much like anything else in
このパターンマッチの構造は実は式なんだ。パターンマッチは式で、Scalaの他のものと同じように
scala that means it can be reduced to a value so the value of this pattern match expression is either
値に評価される。このパターンマッチ式の値は、"first"か"second"か"third"か、
the string first second third or the string composed by the integer plus the suffix th and because it's an
整数に"th"を付けた文字列のどれかになる。式だから
expression we can assign it to a value so pattern matching is the equivalent of a switch expression
valに代入できるんだ。パターンマッチングは他の言語で見たことがあるかもしれないswitch式と同等のものだけど、
that you may have seen in other languages but pattern matching takes things to a whole another level
パターンマッチングはもっとすごいレベルのことができる。
because pattern matching is able to also deconstruct data structures into its constituent parts let me
なぜかというと、データ構造をその構成要素に分解できるからなんだ。
give you an example let me create a small case class that I'm going to name person which has a name
例を見せるね。Personという小さなcase classを作って、nameは
as a string and an age as an int we discussed about case classes in the object orientation video
String型、ageはInt型にしよう。case classについてはオブジェクト指向の動画で説明したよ。
in this mini course so if you don't know what a case class is go ahead and watch that video first all right
このミニコースの中でね。case classが何かわからない人は先にその動画を見てきてね。
so having this defined this case class I will create an instance of that case class let me create a value
このcase classを定義したら、そのインスタンスを作るよ。
called bob as a new person with the string bob and age let's say 43 or something like that you know
bobというvalを、Personのインスタンスで名前は"Bob"、年齢は43とかにしよう。
from the object orientation lecture when we discussed case classes that they don't need to be instantiated
オブジェクト指向の回でcase classについて話した時に、case classはnewキーワードなしで
with a keyword new because the person case class also has a companion object with an apply method so this is
インスタンス化できるって言ったよね。Personのcase classにはapplyメソッドを持つコンパニオンオブジェクトがあるから。
actually person dot apply with the string bob and the age 43 all right now that's not the uh the goal that
つまりこれは実際にはPerson.applyに文字列"Bob"と年齢43を渡してるのと同じなんだ。さて、
i wanted to show here for the case class what i want to show is how to deconstruct a value that you
case classで見せたかったのはそこじゃなくて、どこかから受け取った値を
obtain from somewhere else and decompose it into its constituent parts let me give you an example let me create a
その構成要素に分解する方法なんだ。例を見せるね。
string called person greeting as bob space match and opening close and curly braces and i will add my first
personGreetingというString型のvalを、bob match で波括弧を開いて、
case but instead of passing a definitive value as we did above with the switch expression i'm going to
最初のcaseを追加するよ。さっきのswitch式みたいに確定した値を渡すんじゃなくて、
pass a whole structure like person with a name and an age and i will return the following string hi my name
Person(n, a)みたいに構造全体を渡すんだ。そして次の文字列を返す。"Hi, my name is
is dollar n so the id has already created an s interpolated string for me my name is n and i am
$n"って。IDEが自動的にs補間文字列を作ってくれたね。"my name is n and I am
age years old this is more like a kid's greeting but you get the idea so this case over here is not
a years old"。子供の自己紹介みたいだけど、わかるでしょ。このcaseは
necessarily matching against a definitive value like we did above but it matches bob the value that i'm
上でやったみたいに確定した値にマッチングしてるわけじゃなくて、bobという値を
matching against against a whole entire structure so if bob conforms to the structure person with a name
構造全体に対してマッチングしてるんだ。つまりbobがPerson(name, age)という構造に
and an age then let n and a be the constituent parts of bob as a person so if i have n and a as the
適合するなら、nとaをPersonとしてのbobの構成要素にしてくれる。nとaが
constituent parts of person i can then reuse them at the right hand side of this arrow sign and obviously
Personの構成要素として取り出されたら、矢印の右側で再利用できるんだ。当然
in case i get something else i will return something else as the string so if i print line person greeting
それ以外の場合は"something else"という文字列を返す。personGreetingをprintlnすると
you will see hi my name is bob and i am 43 years old that is because the pattern match expression
"Hi, my name is Bob and I am 43 years old"って表示される。パターンマッチ式が
is able to match bob against this structure and it will automatically assign n to the string bob and a
bobをこの構造に対してマッチングして、nに文字列"Bob"を、aに
to the number 43 and it will inject them into this s interpolated string so if i run this application
数値43を自動的に割り当てて、s補間文字列に注入してくれるんだ。このアプリケーションを
again you will see hi my name is bob and i'm 43 years old now in the object orientation video i mentioned
実行すると、"Hi, my name is Bob and I'm 43 years old"って表示される。オブジェクト指向の動画で
that there are a couple of benefits to defining case classes and one of those benefits now is being able
case classを定義するメリットがいくつかあるって言ったよね。そのメリットのひとつが
to deconstruct them in pattern matching so pattern matching is available mostly for case classes it's
パターンマッチングで分解できることなんだ。パターンマッチングは基本的にcase classで使えるもので、
also available for normal classes if you do a lot of magic behind the scenes i'm not going to talk
普通のクラスでも裏側でいろいろやれば使えるけど、それは
about that because that's really advanced so just bear in mind that pattern matching is only available
かなり上級者向けだから今は触れないよ。今のところは、パターンマッチングは
for case classes for now good so pattern matching can deconstruct case classes
case classでのみ使えると覚えておいてね。よし、パターンマッチングでcase classを分解できるってわかったね。
now pattern matching can deconstruct some other data structures as well for example deconstructing tuples
パターンマッチングは他のデータ構造も分解できるよ。例えばタプルの分解だ。
so let me create a tuple as the tuple bon jovi which is one of my favorite bands and the genre rock
タプルを作るよ。("Bon Jovi", "Rock")っていうタプルだ。僕の好きなバンドのひとつだよ。ジャンルはRockね。
for example you know from the earlier video that we can create tuples by putting some values here
前の動画で見たように、括弧の中にカンマ区切りで値を入れるとタプルが作れるよね。
separated by comma inside these parentheses and this is a tuple you python users i'm sure you know what i'm
Pythonユーザーなら馴染みがあるはず。Scalaではこのタプルを構成要素に分解できる。例えば
talking about now scala can deconstruct these tuples into their constituent parts for example let's call
bandDescriptionっていうvalを作って、
this band description as a tuple space match and open and close some curly braces and i can pass in a case
aTuple match で波括弧を開いて、タプルの構造を表すcaseを書くよ。
that describes the structure of a tuple let's call this band comma genre and on the right hand side of the
(band, genre)みたいに。矢印の右側では
arrow sign i will say that band belongs to the genre dollar genre and in case i get something else i will
"$band belongs to the genre $genre"って返す。それ以外の場合は
return the string i don't know what you're talking about
"I don't know what you're talking about"って返すよ。
all right so if this tuple conforms to a two-member tuple structure then let band and genre be the
さて、このタプルが2要素のタプル構造に適合するなら、bandとgenreを
members of that tuple so that i can then reuse them into this s interpolated string so notice how i'm
そのタプルのメンバーとして取り出せる。そうすればs補間文字列の中で再利用できるんだ。
reading this pattern match expression if the tuple conforms to this structure then let these be the
パターンマッチ式の読み方に注目してね。タプルがこの構造に適合するなら、これらを
members the constituent parts of this tuple so that i can then reuse them on the right hand side
タプルの構成要素として取り出して、矢印の右側で再利用できる、ってことだよ。
you can also deconstruct more complex data structures as well for example decomposing lists so let me
もっと複雑なデータ構造も分解できるよ。例えばリストの分解。
create a list as the list one two three this is a list of integers so if i create for example val list
リストを作るよ。List(1, 2, 3)。整数のリストだね。例えば
description as a list space match space open and close curly brace i can create a case that describes the
listDescriptionというvalを、aList match で波括弧を開いて、
the structure of a list that takes something so the underscore means absolutely anything the number two
リストの構造を記述するcaseを作れる。アンダースコアは何でもOKという意味で、数値の2と
and something else and i will return the string for example list containing two on its second position
もうひとつの何か、って構造だ。この場合は"list containing 2 on its second position"って返すよ。
and in case i get something else i will return unknown list or something like that the underscore presence is not
それ以外の場合は"unknown list"みたいなのを返す。アンダースコアのケースは
mandatory but if the pattern match doesn't match anything it will throw a match error which will
必須じゃないけど、パターンマッチがどれにもマッチしなかったらMatchErrorがスローされて
crash your program this is why for best practice we normally always add an underscore case over here
プログラムがクラッシュする。だからベストプラクティスとして、常にアンダースコアのケースを追加するんだ。
good so notice how we can describe some complex data structures like a structure of a list whose first
よし。複雑なデータ構造も記述できるってわかったね。最初の要素は何でもよくて、
element is something that we don't care about the second element is two the third element is something
2番目の要素が2で、3番目の要素は何でもいい、っていうリストの構造だ。
that we don't care about and that's it so a four element list will not match this pattern a two
だから4要素のリストはこのパターンにマッチしないし、2要素のリストもマッチしない。
element list will not match this pattern and so on and so forth the list must have exactly three elements
リストはちょうど3要素で、1番目と3番目はなんでもよくて、
the first and the third of which we don't care about and the second must be exactly two so notice
2番目がちょうど2でなきゃいけない。ね、パターンマッチングは単純なswitchよりもずっと強力でしょ。
pattern matching is much more powerful than a simple switch one more thing about pattern matching pattern
もうひとつパターンマッチングについて。パターンマッチングは
matching will try all cases in sequence so for example if i inverse these cases so if i put this case
すべてのケースを順番に試すよ。例えば、ケースの順番を逆にして、
first and the case with the list of three elements last because this wild card this underscore matches
このワイルドカードのケースを先にして、3要素リストのケースを後にすると、アンダースコアは
absolutely anything the string that will be returned is unknown list that is because pattern matching will
何にでもマッチするから、返される文字列は"unknown list"になる。パターンマッチングは
try all the cases in sequence so let me change that back now i will end this video with the fact that
ケースを順番に試していくからね。じゃあ元に戻すよ。この動画の最後に言っておくと、
pattern matching is much more powerful than we've written here with lots of complex data structure
パターンマッチングはここで書いたものよりもっとずっと強力で、複雑なデータ構造の
deconstruction name binding and so much more but just to quote tim ferris and his minimum effective dose
分解やname bindingなど、できることはまだまだあるよ。でもTim Ferrissの最小有効量の考え方を借りると、
this code is basically everything that you will need to be able to work with 90 of all pattern matching
ここで書いたコードで、実際のコードベースで見かけるパターンマッチングの
use cases that you will ever see in code bases all right so i hope this was useful in the next video
90%のユースケースに対応できるよ。これが役に立てたらうれしいな。次の動画では
we will talk about some advanced skull stuff that you will probably see in real life if you liked this
実際の現場で見かけるようなScalaの上級テクニックについて話すよ。この動画が
video and found it useful go ahead and click the like button and subscribe to the rock the jvm channel
役に立ったと思ったら、いいねボタンを押してRock the JVMチャンネルを登録してね。
and i'll be posting more free goodies here this video series is also available as a free online course
これからも無料コンテンツを投稿していくよ。この動画シリーズはrockthejvm.comでも
at rock the jvm.com where you will also have the option to download these videos for your offline use
無料オンラインコースとして公開していて、オフライン用に動画をダウンロードすることもできるよ。
and on the rock the jvm site we also have hundreds of hours of premium content dedicated to scala
Rock the JVMのサイトにはScalaやファンクショナルプログラミング、
functional programming akka apache spark and so much more so go ahead and check out rock the jvm.com
Akka、Apache Sparkなどの何百時間ものプレミアムコンテンツもあるから、ぜひrockthejvm.comをチェックしてね。
and i'll be waiting for you in the next video
じゃあ次の動画で待ってるよ。